<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spare your good</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23014A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120428</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855625</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21126</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21126)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1585:26 or 1671:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spare your good</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>in Poules churche yarde by [T. Marsh for] Anthony Kytson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1555?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption on A1r; imprint from colophon, actual printer and suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with Marsh's name in the colophon; first leaf is probably the first leaf of STC (2nd ed.) 23013 (cf. STC 2nd ed. -- "Tp verso line 2 from bottom: 'theym').</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; first leaf, pi1 is torn, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21126:1"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21126:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21126:2"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21126:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Spare your good</head>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21126:3"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven aboute the moneth of maye</l>
               <l>I wene it was the thirde daye</l>
               <l>Of that ſame moneth as I geſſe</l>
               <l>And ſo it was ſo haue I bleſſe</l>
               <l>For I knowe it well by a thinge</l>
               <l>Of the whiche I haue had knowledgynge</l>
               <l>As here after ye ſhall heare full well</l>
               <l>Of a knightes ſone how it befell</l>
               <l>A riche knight there was in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I vnderſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And was a man of greate lande</l>
               <l>and hyght ſyr Thomas perlore</l>
               <l>a ſone he had with his wyfe and no more</l>
               <l>And ſhe was called faire Yſaungrayne</l>
               <l>and their ſone called Rafelyne</l>
               <l>and of this childe ye ſhall heare</l>
               <l>and of his father and his mother dere</l>
               <l>Of his father he was lefe and dere</l>
               <l>So was he of his mother I you enſere</l>
               <l>So it happened vpon a daye</l>
               <l>That this yonge man ſhoulde ſporte and playe</l>
               <l>His father bade hym go amonge wyſe men</l>
               <l>That he might learne ſome good of them</l>
               <l>But this yunge man him bethought</l>
               <l>That after his fathers counſell he wold do nougt</l>
               <l>But to yll company he him drewe</l>
               <l>and learned all vyce and lefte vertue</l>
               <l>Tyll father and mother were deade</l>
               <l>Than coulde he none other rede</l>
               <l>But burye them after the comune vſe</l>
               <l>Other ſorowe woulde he none vſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21126:3"/>But forth he wente to his company anone</l>
               <l>and ſaide ſirs let vs be mery euerychone</l>
               <l>Syr they ſaide welcome be ye truely</l>
               <l>and we all praye you hartely</l>
               <l>To ſyt by vs and kepe company</l>
               <l>So he did and thanked them hertely</l>
               <l>They called anone for meate &amp; drincke of the beſte</l>
               <l>For to eate and drincke as them leſt</l>
               <l>and whan they had eaten and dronken theyr fyll</l>
               <l>Syr they ſaide knowe ye nothinge of oure wyll</l>
               <l>No by my faith he ſaide incontinente</l>
               <l>But by ſaint Thomas of kente</l>
               <l>I woulde haue at the haſarde a caſt or two</l>
               <l>For to learne to caſte the dyce to and fro</l>
               <l>and if here be any body that wyll for money playe</l>
               <l>I haue yet in my purſe money and pledges gaye</l>
               <l>Some be nobles, ſome be crownes of Fraunce</l>
               <l>Haue at all who wyll of this daunce</l>
               <l>One of them anſwered with that worde</l>
               <l>and caſte a bale of dyce on the borde</l>
               <l>and ſaide maiſter Rafeleyne wyll ye haue a fytre</l>
               <l>Haue at all yf ye wyll ſytte</l>
               <l>Maiſter Rafeleyne drewe to his pouche</l>
               <l>Tyll he had loſte coyne and o w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>che</l>
               <l>Than he drewe out pledges freſſhe and gaye</l>
               <l>Tyll all was gone and played awaye</l>
               <l>home he goeth lyke as he were out of his minde</l>
               <l>and ſolde al his goodes before and behynde</l>
               <l>and to harlotes he goeth and to baudes bolde</l>
               <l>For he thought his money ſhoulde euer holde</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21126:4"/>To the tauerne and to the bordell he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndreſt</l>
               <l>For al that his felowſhip d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel him for the beſt</l>
               <l>But at the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te whan all was gone</l>
               <l>Than he began to make his mone</l>
               <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke as here after ye ſhal vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande.</l>
               <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the prolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue</trailer>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Las my good is ſpente I haue no more</l>
               <l>Therfore I am troubled ſore</l>
               <l>with great greuaunce in my herte rote</l>
               <l>To ſpende a pounde was but a ſmall note</l>
               <l>Lyke as I was vſed to do here and there</l>
               <l>Therfore I muſt now mirth forbeare</l>
               <l>Whyche here before I did not vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſhall I now begin to do alace</l>
               <l>Here before I might go in euery place</l>
               <l>Wyth the beſt where ſo euer they wente</l>
               <l>vnto the wine, to the good ale, or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bere al vnſhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
               <l>But for bycauſe gyue no more I maye</l>
               <l>Muſte I be caſte out of al game and play</l>
               <l>In my greuaunce is no remedy I vnderſtand</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What auayleth it me to crye or to complayne then</l>
               <l>Whan my frendes and alſo my kynneſmen</l>
               <l>Maie neither ſe me nor heare me</l>
               <l>Therfore thincke I of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but lytell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted to be</l>
               <l>Thus haue I ſpente al my good out right</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21126:4"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h playenge, wyth drinkynge day and night</l>
               <l>which euery wiſe man wil not do I vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neuer I coulde perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue this great charge</l>
               <l>But my luſte hath brought me in this rage</l>
               <l>The whiche I begin no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to vnderſtand</l>
               <l>That money is lorde of all the lande</l>
               <l>For bycauſe I haue not hadde this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce</l>
               <l>Therfore pouertie and miſerye is tall to my chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
               <l>And am taken of no value I vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſee that they with fingers point after me</l>
               <l>The whyche here before were vſed to prayſe me</l>
               <l>And they let me paſſe by the dore</l>
               <l>The whiche I haue kepte good felowſhippe to fore</l>
               <l>They mocke with me whiche I was wont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to trime</l>
               <l>May not I haue great repentaunce of this luſte</l>
               <l>Ye and muſt ſuffre this I vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whan I was yonge and had good at wyll</l>
               <l>And euery body eate and drancke with me their fyll</l>
               <l>Than they did cal me in euery place</l>
               <l>Now they thincke I am not worth a lace</l>
               <l>Pouertye hath taken me with greate ſorow</l>
               <l>I haue nothinge nor can nothinge borow</l>
               <l>Thus haue I but yll fortune I vnderſtande</l>
               <l>therefore ſpare your good that ye haue in hand</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21126:5"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ue thought in my minde</l>
               <l>Coulde I any good get or find</l>
               <l>I woulde not caſte it awaye euery del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Lyke as my felowſhippe did my counſel</l>
               <l>Whan I was vſed to beare money be my ſyde</l>
               <l>I thought not that it ſhoulde thus from me ſlyde</l>
               <l>Thus was I not wyſe I vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Therefore ſpare your good that you haue in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Might I yet that daye liue</l>
               <l>That my frendes woulde me giue</l>
               <l>Some thinge where with all</l>
               <l>I might get richeſſe and honeſte princypall</l>
               <l>I woulde thanke them nowe and than amonge</l>
               <l>But certes my thinketh they tary to longe</l>
               <l>Therfore I muſt ſuffer be it ſwete or ſoure I vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whan any body hath any richeſſe</l>
               <l>Euery body him worſhippeth both more and leſſe</l>
               <l>But and he haue nothinge in value</l>
               <l>He is nothinge ſette by perdue</l>
               <l>And if he come hyther or els where</l>
               <l>Euerie bodye fleeth from him as he the deuyll were</l>
               <l>Ful often chaungeth his courage I vnderſtande</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare youre good that ye haue in hande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that hath nothinge is taken of no value</l>
               <l>And wyll not do after good counſell perdue</l>
               <l>Lyke as of me ye maye example take</l>
               <l>Howe of ryot and other games was vſed to make</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21126:5"/>Who ſo euer in the worlde yf ryot me bethought</l>
               <l>I coulde it lyghtly helpe for to be wrought</l>
               <l>whiche is now bitter it was than ſwete at that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherfore ſholde not I take now ſorowe againe</l>
               <l>Ye certes there is none that wyl me any thing lene</l>
               <l>Euen thus the whele of fortune renneth</l>
               <l>And if good lucke dyd tame I ſholude not be wete</l>
               <l>If it be good lucke or yll happe</l>
               <l>It commeth to him that ſhall haue it at a clappe</l>
               <l>Euery body maie ſe by me in this ſtande</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A man maye well a good felow be</l>
               <l>In the wine, in good ale, in bere where ſo it be</l>
               <l>and yf he thinke for the comune profyte alſo</l>
               <l>Here or there where ſo euer he go</l>
               <l>Thus may a man haunte mirth and gaine</l>
               <l>If he do it not by meaſure he is to blame</l>
               <l>For in euery thinge meaſure is good I vnderſtand</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hand</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Farewell I ſette you al this teſtamente</l>
               <l>Who wyll learne this ſhall be vnſhente</l>
               <l>and can kepe him amonge good company</l>
               <l>Shall be fre of al ſorowe and myſerye</l>
               <l>Who ſo euer taketh this teſtamente in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
               <l>Pouertye and myſerye ſhall not fall to his chaunce</l>
               <l>Hys good his worſhippe ſhall he kepe I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de</l>
               <l>Therfore ſpare your good that ye haue in hande</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21126:6"/>
            <trailer>I Here endeth a lytell tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tyſe very profitable for euery yonge man and yonge woman cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Syrs ſpare your good.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London in Poules churche yarde by Anthony Kytſon.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>GEMINI.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21126:6"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
